Mitochondria or cellbean by their prison
name are these incredibly important
organels inside of our cells because
they provide our cells with energy but
also protect us from cancer and play a
vital role in hormone production among
many many other roles. Unfortunately, as
we age, mitochondria can also become
aged or damaged over time making them
and your cells suffer functionally. So,
while we might know that exercise
improves mitochondrial function, does
that still remain true for older folks?
And if so, to what degree? Okay, now for
the hook. The answer will shock you.
Well done, Nick. Now they're hooked.
We're going to be relying on two studies
that looked into the effect of exercise
in older individuals and the
mitochondrial effect. The first, this
one, recruited 20 year olds and 70 year
olds and had them perform aerobic
exercise for 12 weeks. Specifically,
they performed supervised cycling. And
what happened to their mitochondria?
Okay. Well, I'll show you some
mitochondrial measures, but these
measures are a bit deceptive, as I'll
explain shortly. Here, we're looking at
various proteins found inside your cells
that correspond to mitochondria. PGC1
alpha is a biogenesis protein as in it
allows for more mitochondria to be
produced. CS is citrate synthes involved
in mitochondrial metabolism as are these
other proteins here. Actually, the light
bars are the younger participants and
the black bars are those in their 70s.
Notice how all the bars are going up and
notice the cross up top. That all
indicates that young and old are able to
increase the amount of all of these
proteins in their cells by exercising.
There's some more to this story that
we'll get to, but it seems, and I can't
stress that word enough, it seems like
there's no difference between the young
and the older, as in both experience a
similar increase in these proteins. The
same is true when looking at proteins
involved in mitochondrial dynamics.
These proteins are involved in the
fusion and fision of mitochondria. More
specifically, mitochondria have the
ability to split themselves into new
mitochondria or to fuse together into a
single
mitochondrian. And these are some of the
proteins involved in that process. And
again, we see similar increases due to
exercise with no seeming difference
between young and older. Okay, so we can
for sure say that exercise impacts
mitochondria and still it occurs later
in life. Now a few things for what seem
and what actually are. If we look at V2
measurements, these are measurements of
oxygen consumption and while not
exclusively reliant on mitochondria,
they are tightly related. One, you'll
notice that both groups improve from
exercise. Yet the younger individuals
experience greater improvement noted by
the dollar sign indicating an
interaction effect. Crosses and dollar
signs. What is this? The papacy.
Heyo. Okay. So why the difference here?
And no difference on the mitochondrial
measures. If we bring back the
mitochondrial measures and keep the V2
measurements and we pay attention to the
vertical axis and the units, the V2 is
measured in absolute units and the
mitochondrial measures are in relative
units. So that means that while the
relative improvement might be a 50%
increase for both young and older, the
absolute starting protein numbers for
something like I don't know MFN1 might
have been 10 for the younger individuals
and four for the older individuals.
Which means that the absolute end result
would be 15 and six. A big difference.
Of course, I'm making up the numbers,
but you get the point. The relative
change is not indicative of the absolute
effect in this instance. So that
explained, the reality is older
individuals do experience mitochondrial
changes from exercise, but the amount of
change in absolute sense is likely
smaller than for younger individuals.
But do not despair, do not weep, my
elder, good news travels from far away
lands, and those lands be another study.
In this second study, researchers
recruited three groups of people. Active
young individuals, older active
individuals, and the older sedentary
individuals. Then instead of applying an
exercise intervention, they simply ran a
battery of tests on these people to
collect a bunch of data based on their
activity level and age. So this is
called a comparative study. First off,
let me show you the cross-sections of
their legs. The green there, as
indicated, is skeletal muscle. The
yellow is fat tissue between the
musculature and the red is the fat
tissue surrounding the musculature. The
YA are the young, the OA are the old
active and the OS are the old sedentary.
These images always stood out to me
since the beginning of my exercise
physiology degree. I mean, they're
incredible reminders of how much power
exercise has at preserving our
physiology. The old active individuals
and the young active individuals are
more alike than people the same age who
are sedentary. That's crazy cool. I
mean, there's more data on this
indicating more similarity with younger
individuals than the same aged
individuals that I can cover in future
content. If you're interested, just let
me know. For now, let's look at the
mitochondrial effects. I did mention
some good news for ye old lads and
lasses. Okay, I'll stop. Among the most
important proteins in your mitochondria
are these five called the electron
transport chain. Now, I won't go over
their function, but just know that
they're responsible for the production
of your cellular energy called ATP. So,
if we look at that data, and you'll
notice the five proteins are listed on
the bottom there, 1 through five in
Roman numeral. The gray bars are the
young individuals and the green bars are
the in the middle are the old active
individuals. And the final bar on the
right, the blue is the old sedentary
individuals. The higher the bar, the
more of these proteins exist in the
muscle tissue that was probed. Now, each
bar is the average result. And you'll
note that the individual dots offering
information on each individual result
and indicates the spread of the data.
You should focus on the letters A and B.
If the letters are the same, there's no
difference between the groups. And it
it's also true if the letters are
different like A and B, there's a
statistically significant difference
between those groups. I'll give you an
easy summary now, but at least you can
verify after me now that you know how to
read this. The summary is that both
active groups, regardless of age, had
greater levels of these key
mitochondrial proteins relative to the
sedentary older individuals. Not only
that, the levels were comparable between
young and old active individuals. That's
huge. I'd speculate that if they had
more participants in each group, we
might detect some minor differences
between the young and the old active,
but as it stands, there's no difference,
which is wild. Oh, and if you're
wondering what the top part of the data
is, it's the raw molecular data. I'll
leave that for those with a cell and
molecular biology background to
appreciate. No point really going over
it now. Okay, so mitochondrial proteins
responsible for energy generation are
greater in active individuals. But guess
what? The researchers directly measured
energy generation from mitochondria
isolated from these individuals. So the
proteins are like inspecting the car at
standstill, but now we get to inspect
the car in motion. Also, I have a
seminar on improving mitochondria
through exercise. And there's some
additional fascinating mitochondrial
results that I won't be able to get into
in this video that you're watching that
I cover in the extended version of this
video. Both of those, so the seminar and
the extended version of this video,
including all of my other work and
analyses, are included for the physionic
insiders. If you're interested, the link
is in the description of the video that
you're currently watching.
Now the car in motion, the actual ATP
measurements coming from mitochondria
are here. Amazingly, these results
confirm the protein measurements that
active individuals, regardless of age,
generate the same amount of ATP per unit
of time. Incredible. Now, while this is
excellent news, there are some important
pieces of context for this study.
Notably, this is a comparative study.
So, it does not control for any other
variables like nutrition, sleep habits,
and other important aspects of health.
Also, while the results could be and
even likely due to exercise, they could
also be somewhat or even fully caused by
some other variable like just living a
healthier lifestyle as a whole. I
suppose in the grand scheme of things,
who cares, right? Oh, the horror. Living
a healthy lifestyle improves
mitochondria instead of it being
exclusively exercise. The horror.
Anyway, it's still important to point
out because I don't want us to
overinterpret these data. In the end,
these data indicate that aerobic
endurance exercise does lead to changes
in mitochondria and likely improves
mitochondrial function regardless of
age. Beyond that, some metrics indicate
that being active and healthy, even 30
to 40 years older than someone else can
preserve significant mitochondrial
function. Alternatively, to learn more
about improving your mitochondria, check
out this linked video. Cheers.
[Music]